Frederick Newton Arvin papers, 1900 - 1963 (bulk 1924 - 2001)
Smith College Archives
Frederick Newton Arvin papers
1900 - 2001
1924 - 1963
Arvin, Newton, 1900 - 1963.
42 UUID:c98748f0-5948-4c55-b1d4-c4f19cce366d
2 boxes ( .6 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Faculty. Professor of English Language and Literature from 1922 - 1960. Arrested on charges of moral turpitude in 1959 by the City of Northampton, MA, he pled guilty to the charges and was retired from Smith College by the Board of Trustees in 1960.
(Frederick) Newton Arvin was born on August 9, 1900 in Valparaiso, Indiana. After graduating summa cum laude from Harvard University in 1921, he taught private school in Detroit before joining the faculty at Smith College as an Instructor of English in 1922.
Over the next decade, his career soared. He was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1935 and was subsequently named a full professor at Smith College (1940). In 1939 he became a trustee at Yaddo, a writer's colony in Saratoga Springs, New York. While visiting in 1946 he met and began a two-year affair with Truman Capote. Capote's 1948 novel Other Voices, Other Rooms was dedicated to Arvin. Arvin went on to win the 1951 National Book Award in non-fiction for his book Herman Melville (1950).
As Margot Cleary wrote in Hampshire Life (1991), "Newton Arvin's life was a Jekyll and Hyde affair, a mixture of professional acclaim and personal scandal." Despite a brief marriage to Mary Jordan Garrison (Class of 1931), Arvin was living as a closeted gay man. The marriage ended in 1940 with both Garrison and Arvin suffering numerous breakdowns as a result.
During Labor Day weekend in 1960, police raided Arvin's home and confiscated thousands of pictures of male models that were considered pornographic. He was charged with possession and distribution of pornographic materials and though he initially pleaded innocence, he later accepted a finding of guilty. His arrest, and the confiscation of his journals, led to the arrests of several other men in the community including two colleagues at Smith College. The Board of Trustees voted to have Arvin 'retired' in 1960 to the vehement protest of prominent faculty, colleagues and alumnae. Arvin was admitted to Northampton State Hospital for suicidal depression and remained confined for the duration of the ordeal; diagnosed with pancreatic cancer, her died March 21, 1963.
The Newton Arvin papers contain biographic materials, clippings, correspondence, photographs, reports and other administrative documents covering Arvin's career as a faculty member at Smith College.
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Biographical Material (1951 - 1960)
Series II: Publications (1924 - 1958)
Series III: Awards (1935 - 1984)
Series IV: Correspondence (1957)
Series V: Morals Case
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives except where noted in the finding aid.
The Frederick Newton Arvin papers were created over a period of time from a variety of sources and donated to the College Archives.
Arvin, Newton, 1900-1963.; Homosexuality and education -- Massachusetts; Smith College -- Faculty -- Biography; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980
Newton Arvin papers, 1865 - 1963 (bulk 1913 - 1963, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College
Van Wyck Brooks Papers. University of Pennsylvania Library
Truman Capote Award, University of Iowa
- Series I: Biographical Material 1951 - 1960
  Contains information about the life of Frederick Newton Arvin, materials pertaining to his arrest and information supplied for his obituary.
- Series II: Publications 1924 - 1958
  Contains articles published by Arvin on topics such as religion, criticism and literary judgement. A copy of Stacey Sklar's undergraduate thesis regarding Arvin's arrest and conviction is also available.
- Series III: Awards 1935 - 1984
  Contains materials regarding his Guggenheim Fellowship, his award from the National Institute of Arts and Letters and the University of Iowa Truman Capote Award.
- Series IV: Correspondence 1957 - 1998
  Contains letters pertaining to Arvin's professional life.
- Series V: Morals Case 1957 - 1963
  [restricted pending request to College Archivist] Materials from the Office of the President regarding the Morals Case of 1960. Contains correspondence, reports, clippings, and legal records.
- Series I: Biographical Material
  - biographical information and obituaries 1951 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - articles and photographs 1932 - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Publications
  - publications 1924 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Ground of Literary Judgement" 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III: Awards
  - awards and prizes 1935 - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - acceptance speech, National Book Award 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Correspondence
  - correspondence 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - articles pertaining to his arrest 1960 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stacey Sklar, B.A. thesis 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series V: Morals Case
  - Faculty File various (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Morals Case April 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Pornography Case: General 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Edward Spofford 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Joel Dorius 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Alumnae Letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Faculty Letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Public Letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - non-Smith faculty letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - parents letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - student letters 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - news clippings 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)